A Finding Aid to the Jules Olitski Papers, 1950-2012, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Jules Olitski papers
1950-2012
Archives of American Art
Olitski, Jules, 1922-2007
AAA.olitjule
Archival Resource Key
3.2 Linear feet
The papers of artist and educator Jules Olitski measure 3.2 linear feet and date from 1950-2012. The collection sheds light on Olitski's career through writing files that consist of drafts, edits, and some correspondence; printed material such as newspaper clippings and articles, exhibition material, and published writings; portrait photographs of the artist; and sound and video recordings from interviews and lectures.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research. Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center.
Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Scope and Contents
The papers of artist and educator Jules Olitski measure 3.2 linear feet and date from 1950-2012. The collection sheds light on Olitski's career through writing files that consist of drafts, edits, and some correspondence; printed material such as newspaper clippings and articles, exhibition material, and published writings; portrait photographs of the artist; and sound and video recordings from interviews and lectures.
The majority of the collection consists of printed material that provides comprehensive coverage of Olitski's career including announcements, catalogs, and newspaper clippings from Olitski's exhibitions at galleries and museums. Sound and video recordings are of interviews with Olitski related to exhibitions of his work and of lectures given by Olitski at Brown University, the University of Miami, and the National Museum of American History, and other locations. The bulk of these recordings date from the 1990s.
Biographical / Historical
Jules Olitski (1922-2007) was a painter, sculptor, and educator in New York, New York, who established himself as one of the leaders of the abstract expressionist movement in the United States during the 1950s-1960s.
Olitski was born in the Ukraine, and moved to New York in 1923 after his father, a commissar, was executed. By 1935, Olitski had developed an interest in art and was awarded a scholarship at the Pratt Institute where he began taking classes in 1939. Soon after he attended the National Academy of Design until 1942 when he enlisted in the United States Army.
In 1949 Olitski studied sculpture with Ossip Zadkine in the Zadkine School of Sculpture in France, and the next year attended the Academia de la Grande Chaumiere in Paris. He then moved back to the United States for his higher education, earning a master's degree from New York University. Olitski became an associate professor of art at the State University of New York, New Paltz in 1954. He held several more teaching positions throughout the 1950s and 1960s in New York and Vermont.
From the 1970s-2000s Olitski received honorary degrees from Keen State College, Hartford Art School, and Southern New Hampshire University, and held solo shows at the Corcoran Gallery of Art in Washington, D.C., Knoedler Contemporary Art in New York, La Musee de Valence in France, and the Drabinsky Friedland Gallery in Toronto. He also participated in several major group exhibitions around the world including American Drawings, 1964 (1964) at the Solomon Guggenheim Museum, New York Painting and Sculpture: 1940-1970 (1970) at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, and The Green Mountain Boys - Caro, Feeley, Noland and Olitski at Bennington in the 1960's (1998), and exhibited elsewhere in Vermont and New York, and many other locations.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated in 2012 and 2013 by the Olitski Family Estate via Lauren Olitski Poster, director of the estate and Olitsky's daughter.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged as four series.
Series 1: Writing Files, 1965-1976 (Box 1; 10 folders)
Series 2: Printed Material, 1950-2012 (Box 1-3; 2.3 linear feet)
Series 3: Photographs, 1967-2006 (Box 3; 7 folders)
Series 4: Recorded Interviews and Lectures, 1977-2003 (Box 3-4; .7 linear feeet)
Sound recordings; Interviews; Video recordings; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Abstract expressionism; Educators -- New York (State) -- New York
- Writing Files, 1965-1976; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 10 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Included are drafts of several articles and exhibition catalog essays written about Olitski throughout his career. Some of the folders may contain edits and comments made by Olitski and the authors, printed material, and scant correspondence.
  Arrangement
  Files are arranged chronologically, with undated material at the end of the series.
  - "Jules Olitski New Paintings," By Michael Fried, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Jules Olitski: Paintings, 1963-1967Essay Draft for Catalog, Michael Fried, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Catalog Draft for Pittsburgh Institute of Contemporary Art, By Rosalind Krauss, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Visit to Jules Olitski's Studio," Unknown, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The Sculpture of Jules Olitski," Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin, By Kenworth Moffett, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "On Order in the Paintings of Jules Olitski," By Ken Carpenter; Notes by Olitski, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Conversations with Jules Olitski," By Frederich Bach, 1974, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Olitski, Cubism, and Transparency," E. A. Carmean Jr., 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "The Life of Drawing of Jules Olitski," Cora Kelley Ward (Unpublished), 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Untitled Manuscript, C.W. Post Show Review, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Printed Material, 1950-2012; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 2.3 Linear feet Box 1-3
  Articles and clippings include writings and reviews regarding Olitski, his shows, his artwork, the abstract expressionist art scene that Olitski was active in, and more by critics John Canaday, Irving Sandler, Hilton Kramer, and others. Also found here are advertisements for Olitski's shows and excerpts about Olitski from books. Exhibition material includes announcements, invitations, catalogs, and some posters from group and solo shows. Published writings by Olitski consist of writings on art, his own career, and poetry. The series also includes ephemeral materials related to Olitski's lectures and other events, bulletins and newsletters, and reproductions of Olitski's art.
  - Articles and Clippings, 1950-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11-22)
  - Articles and Clippings, 2001-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Articles and Clippings, Foreign, 1951-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Invitations, Brochures, Solo Shows, 1967-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4-9)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Solo Shows, 1959-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10-15)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Invitations, Brochures, Group Shows, 1974-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Group Shows, 1965-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Lectures and Events, 1988-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Organization and Museum, Bulletins and Newsletters, 1965-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Published Writings by Olitski, 1955-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
  - Reproductions, Abrams Publishing, "Abrams Appointment Diary 1989", 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Photographs, 1967-2006; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 7 Folders Box 3
  The series consists of portrait snapshots taken of Olitski throughout his career and photographs of the artist at an awards dinner.
  - Olitski Portraits Taken By Lawrence J. Hyman, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Olitski Portraits Taken By Helen Miljakovich, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Olitski Portraits in Islamorada, Florida Taken By Jim Roberts, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Olitski Portraits Taken By Richard Mandelkorn, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Olitski Portraits in Bear Island Studio, Meredith, NH Taken By Helen Miljakovich, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Olitski Portraits Taken By Erik LaPrade, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Olitski at American Academy Arts and Letters Dinner, 2006 April 6; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Recorded Interviews and Lectures, 1977-2003; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Box 3-4
  Found here are sound and video recordings from various interviews, lectures, and talks given by Olitski at universities, museums, and on radio. Of particular note is a video recording from Olitski's dedication of his work, "Elyon," at the Beth Tzedec Congregation Synagogue in 1990.
  Series is arranged chronologically.
  - Interview with Kenworth Moffett, Boston Museum of Fine Arts, 1977; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
  - Olitski Talk at University of Miami, 1986; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Beth Tzedec Holocaust Memorial Dedication, 1990 April 22; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Olitski Talk at Brown University, 1991 December 6; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Olitski Talk at Yale University, 1993 May 6; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Olitski Talk at University of Miami, 1994 February 25; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Colors of Invention," Olitski and Mark Golden, 1997 November 16; Archival Resource Key; 3 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Interview with John Walters, National Public Radio, 2003 September 30; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 4, Folder 3)